Guide to the John Tuttle and Arvilla Raplee Andrews papers, 1843-1982
Tuttle, John and Andrews Arvilla Raplee papers, 1843-1982
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John Tuttle and Arvilla Raplee Andrews papers, 1843-1982.
3790
John Tuttle Andrews, 1842-1916.
2.1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, military records, genealogies, photographs, and diaries.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence (1856-88) of John Andrews, Arvilla Raplee, friends, and relatives, including Civil War letters of Andrews. Also, military records, Civil War diaries, and other papers.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
John T. Andrews was born on March 9, 1842 in Reading, New York. He attended Alfred University and Union College, from which he graduated in 1864. In August 1864 he enlisted in Company D of the 179th Regiment of the New York Volunteers and served until June 23, 1865. In 1866 he married Arvilla Raplee. Andrews worked in the furniture and undertaking business in Dundee, New York, studied law in Penn Yan, New York with B.W. Franklin, and was admitted to the bar in 1870. In 1873 he began manufacturing paper. In 1881 he was elected to the Assembly from Yates County, and from 1890-1894 he was postmaster at Penn Yan.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence (1856-88) of John Andrews, Arvilla Raplee, friends, and relatives, including Civil War letters of Andrews, with a series from "Em" in March 1865 concerning a pregnancy she terminated, letters of Byron L. Sawyer of the 39th Illinois Volunteers, and of Charles E. Stamp, who died in the Battle of South Mountain; letters (1899-1911) from the couple to their son, Charles Tubbs Andrews; and letters written by Mary E. Wager, who contributed to the Rural New Yorker under the pseudonym "Minnie Mintwood." Also, records of the 179th Regiment, New York Volunteers, in which Andrews served with the rank of Captain, including military orders, pay department receipts, muster rolls, assignments of equipment, insignia, and other items; a manuscript oration that John delivered at the "Decoration of Soldiers' Graves" (Penn Yan, 1870); and newspaper clippings (ca. 1860-65) concerning the war. Also, manuscript genealogies and photographs of portraits of John and Arvilla. Correspondentss include Andrews' uncle, John Tuttle Andrews I, and Edwin C., Emma, Ettie, Homer, Lucinda, and Mollie Andrews; Frank M. Booth; Theodore H. Bryant; Frank M. Clark; Lizzie Conderman; Emma Currier; Frank Eaton; Libbie Ellis; "Mate" (Mary) Gifford; Stephen F. Griffeth; Frank Ideson; Mollie A. Langworthy; Edward P. Magoun; Ira Raplee; Simon L. Rood; Andrew H. Stamp; John R. and Libbie Taylor; Zelima Treman; Charles Tubbs; Philip Taylor Vanzile; Annie M. Washburn; W.E. Wisner; and C.D. Wood.
Includes six Civil War diaries of John Tuttle Andrews, concerning enlistment, recruitment, Petersburg battles, soldiers' desertion, trials, and executions, African-American soldiers' participation, the end of the War and Lincoln's assassination, and his mustering out in 1865.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Andrews, John Tuttle, 1842-1916.; Andrews, Arvilla Raplee, 1843-1902.; Andrews, Charles Tubbs.; Andrews, Edwin C.; Andrews, Emma.; Andrews, Ettie.; Andrews, Homer.; Andrews, John Tuttle,; Andrews, Lucinda.; Andrews, Mollie.; Booth, Frank M.; Bryant, Theodore H.; Clark, Frank M.; Conderman, Lizzie.; Currier, Emma.; Eaton, Frank.; Ellis, Libbie.; Gifford, Mary.; Griffeth, Stephen F.; Ideson, Frank.; Langworthy, Mollie A.; Magoun, Edward P.; Mintwood, Minnie.; Raplee, Ira.; Rood, Simon L.; Sawyer, Byron L.; Stamp, Andrew H.; Stamp, Charles E.; Taylor, John R.; Taylor, Libbie.; Treman, Zelima.; Tubbs, Charles.; Vanzile, Philip Taylor.; Wager, Mary E.; Washburn, Annie M.; Wisner, W.E.; Wood, C.D.; New York (State).Legislature.Assembly--Officials and employees.; United States.Army.New York Volunteers, 179th.Company D.; United States.Army.Illinois Volunteers, 39th.
Subjects:
Abortion.; Pregnancy, Unwanted.; Lawyers.
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Form and Genre Terms:
Genealogies.; Photographs.; Speeches.; Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, 1856-1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Jan.-Aug. 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Sept.-Dec. 1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Jan.-May 1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, June-Sept. 1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Oct.-Dec. 1863 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Jan.-May 1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, June-Oct. 1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Nov.-Dec. 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, Jan. 1865 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, Feb.-Apr. 1865 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, May-Dec. 1865 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, Jan.-Feb. 1866 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Mar.-Dec. 1866 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1867-1868 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Jan.-Apr. 1869 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, May-Dec. 1869 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1870-1871 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1899-1900 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1901 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, Apr.-Dec. 1901 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Misc. correspondence, 1865-1874 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Military, 1863, Jan.-Aug. 1864 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Military, Sept. 1864 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Military, Oct.-Nov. 1864 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Military, Dec. 1864 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Military, Jan.-Feb. 1865 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Military, Mar.-May 1865 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Military, June-Dec. 1865 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Military, 1864-1865 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Oration, May 30, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Mary E. Wager, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Photographs (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Newspaper clippings, ca. 1860-1865 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Military insignia (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Unprocessed material: Walkerbilt Woodwork, Inc.: invoices; muster rolls, 179th N.Y. Volunteers, Civil War; genealogy; real estate related miscellany; family documents; Keuka Lake Shore Property Owners Association files (Box 4)
- Muster Rolls: 179th N. Y. Volunteers, 1864-1865 (Box 5)
- John T. Andrews: College expenses and journal, 1861-January, 1863 (Box 5)
- John T. Andrews: Expenses and war journal, September 1864 (Box 5)
- John T. Andrews, A. B., 1st Lieut. Co. "D" 179th N. Y. V. 2nd Brigade, 2nd Division, 9th Army Corps., Army of the Potomac: war journal, November 1st, 1864 (Box 5)
- John T. Andrews, ...: November 25, 1864 (Box 5)
- John T. Andrews, ...: February 20, 1865 (Box 5)
- Union College Civil War Record, 1861-1865 (Box 5)
- Muster Rolls: 179th N. Y. Volunteers, 1864-1865 (Box 5)